Okay, we are going to go ahead and get started.
Thank you guys for coming.
Again, another time slot with a bit of competition.
But you guys are the smart ones I can see.
This is Simon Martinelli who needs no introduction.
If you've been involved in the Java community, he is a legend there.
And he's going to be talking about
some lessons learned from spec driven development.
Let's give Simon a hand.
Hey. Welcome everybody.
Let me start by telling a story.
So I'm in a sports club.
I'm from Switzerland and I live in a very small town and we do events.
So we are mainly doing track and field, and we have competitions for kids
already for 45 years and since 1997, I'm doing software for them
because I realized that doing competition and doing competition
ranking list and stuff like that needs a lot of people.
Back in the days, like we have 12 to 15 people
and now it's just me using software, doing that for them.
But that's not the only thing that we do.
We also have different events and we always need volunteers.
And it was in summer 2024 when we had public holiday in Switzerland.
Someone of the club came to me and said, hey Sam, we have an issue.
We have volunteer management system, but that's outdated and doesn't work anymore.
So you're a software engineer and I heard about this AI stuff.
You can certainly do that better. Let's go.
And I said, okay, why not?
And I started to use windsurf.
That was around fall 2024.
And that was relatively fast.
And I had a volunteer management system.
But the problem was some one else from Music Festival approached
me and said, hey, I heard that you're building a volunteer management system.
We need that as well.
And then I had an issue.
I had no clue what I was implementing, and I had no no clue how I could change
the features so that it will fulfill the requirements of this music festival.
And this brought me to spec-driven development
as I was already already introduced.
I'm doing mostly Java development.
I'm a consultant in Switzerland for 17 years and I'm working for insurance
companies, wholesale, retail, government,
large enterprises mostly, and I'm doing business applications.
So I don't do tools, I don't do products, I do business applications.
And during that time, and I was kind of lost, I found a website.
It was called AI native.
You may know it as Tessl.
And I found an article from Simon Maple,
and he was writing about AI 90 development, and that kept my attention.
And I read about spec-driven development.
But at that time, spectrum development was relatively new.
So the term spectrum development is very old, right?
That's from the 2000 or maybe late 90s.
But the spec-driven development with AI was relatively new.
So I started to think about what could specs be.
And because I'm doing business applications, I had a different take,
probably on spec-driven development, and I tried to find a way to do that.
And so in the meanwhile, if we look at the spec-driven development
ecosystem, there are flavors of spec-driven development.
And there is one process centric.
That's my process.
I created this a unified process.
I will show you that in a minute.
But on the other hand, we have tools.
We have Amazon Kiro, we have GitHub spec kit, we have BMT method.
These are all great tools.
And also Tesla created spec-driven tools back then.
Sorry, 2025, but they are all, in my opinion,
at least to developer centric.
And I try to cover the whole software development
lifecycle, especially for enterprises where you not are solar planner.
You're someone in a larger team
with different roles in a large organization,
and there's a website called AI Unified Process.
Let me switch that.
And there you will see kind of a diagram with some colors.
So the colors mean that you usually if you're on a green field
I will talk about brownfield as well because I'm rarely on greenfield projects.
You start with a vision and then you start gathering requirements.
However you would do that.
By the way there is the International Requirements
Engineering Board and they just created something called a microgrid angel.
It's called AI for requirements engineering.
And they have prompting guide skills and stuff.
They are working on that.
How requirements engineer can be speed up with AI.
And then we have testing and stuff like that.
And the green thing is probably what's interesting here.
I was thinking about what could be good specs that A understands,
but also all stakeholders in the project can understand.
And I ended up with system use cases by the way, who knows.
System use cases? Who knows that?
Not a lot of people as I saw.
So system use cases were created by
back in 1987.
And then later on we had UML and ROP and stuff like that.
That was that movement, late 80s, early 90s.
But I was using this muse cases for when I was working for Swiss Railways
early 2000, and this quite worked well as a communication
specification between stakeholders and developers back then.
And I thought, okay,
if that worked back then, why shouldn't it work together with AI?
And then we need something else.
I call it the entity model, but it's more like a domain model.
So it depends if you're doing domain driven design or how you work.
These are the more or less usually the data at the end.
But we need to model that and these things together
with some software architecture I will talk about that later.
Can be used to directly generate code, because the difference from my approach
to the tool approach is the tool approach is always the same.
So usually if you look at Amazon Kiro
for example, you have product requirements document.
From that you generate some plan and out of the plan there will be tasks.
And finally AI will implement the tasks.
I skipped the plant task phase.
I just use communication entity model and generate code directly.
So now this music is are not enough because usually there's a UI for example.
Or if you build an API, you have an API spec.
So you need additional information to that.
So the system use case just defines the behavior.
But how it looks can be, for example, a Figma design that you can integrate
with MCP server and directly interact with Figma out of that.
And then usually code is generated and test is generated.
The question is in which order.
So I'm mostly doing full stack development.
That means I have a UI.
And if you have a UI, test driven
development is difficult because you first need to figure out how
the UI will look like before you can start to create the tests.
If you do APIs, for example, I would always go for test driven development.
So start with the tests and then use the tests also to derive the code generation.
And finally, as we can see always there is a review phase.
So most often things are reviewed.
The question is how much review do you need.
And that's all about risk management.
So I'm currently working
on the modernization of an ERP system for the largest wholesale
company in Switzerland.
And if you look at the near system, you have different modules
in the system that don't have all the same.
How should I say criticality.
So that means if you have the product management or the inventory part,
if that doesn't work,
that's probably not even a problem, because people that are working with
that inventory management system, they can just go and grab a coffee.
If the auto management system doesn't work, that's
more of a problem because then the company probably will lose money, right?
So you should do risk management
and then decide how much review your code probably needs.
But that's not different from AI
or manual driven development that that's just how it works.
Now let's have a look in the detail.
So if we have a greenfield project for example.
We would start with with the specs.
So the specs means we have some requirements.
Engineers, product owners, business analyst.
Depending on how the people are called in your organization
and they create the entity model and use cases.
So they can also derive that directly from requirements, for example.
And then we will have a phase where we can review that.
So there will be some thing like definition of done.
And the software engineer together with AI and the requirements engineer
will decide when the use case is done or the specification is done.
And then we use the agent and the agent comes with.
But a lot of people were already talking about.
So we need skills MCP guidelines, guardrails, whatever.
We will see that in a minute in a demo.
But because we don't do the plan and task phase, we need that in the middle.
That is probably the most important thing of the whole process.
So that means the skill must match the outcome.
That means we need skills that knows how the code and test should be generated.
And that's not always the same.
So I'm working currently for six customers with that process.
And all the skills are different because I have customers
that use React and Spring Boot or just use and Spring Boot
that's a framework or are using angular and quarks.
So I have a variety of different frameworks
and also some in-house frameworks
maybe that need to be working in in that context.
Now that's a greenfield project, but I really rarely do that.
What I do mostly is software modernization.
So I'm doing modernization for enterprise applications for about eight years now.
And there I just changed the process.
That means I extract
use case and entity model from code and tests and documentation.
Maybe I have confidence here or whatever, because usually the documentation
is spread around multiple artifacts that we have,
and then we have the entity model and the use cases.
They will be revised or reviewed by the business people.
And then we generate the new code, because there are a lot of IDs
that we can directly transform, maybe from COBOL to travel.
So that's also something that anthropic is, is telling us.
But that never worked.
So we did that like 30 years ago COBOL to C, or COBOL to C++, or something.
But that's not helpful because that's just lift and shift.
And modernization is not lift and shift.
Modernization is rethinking how people are working
with the software, integrating features that maybe are not there.
And because of this reverse engineering, we also have
a positive feedback from the end users because we are not transforming
from one technology to another, because regarding our use case and entity model.
And we can integrate new features because usually you don't do that.
So the guideline when we started with the modernization project
two years ago was we want to have the exact same system
just in another technology,
and you don't add new features because we don't want to introduce new bugs.
And now we can just do that because we just change the specification.
Now the question is maybe why use cases?
Because user usually people are using stories
or any other product requirements document.
The point is use cases are very well defined
and even AI knows how to write use cases because it's around for a very long time.
That means we have use case that has usually that form, right.
We have precondition post conditions and we have scenarios.
Usually you have a main success scenario and then you have alternative flows.
And if we compare that with user stories we can see that user
stories are just a collection or use cases a collection of user story usually.
So one user story is usually
a flow in a use case.
And in my opinion or in my experience, use
cases are better than user stories because they are simply bigger.
And so we have that.
And I created a small project.
So do we have Java developers here?
By the way?
You certainly know the application that I was already displaying before.
We have the Spring PetClinic.
So that's kind of a demo project from the spring framework.
Just some history.
Spring was using Pet Clinic because before we had Travel
Enterprise Edition and they had Pet Shop and they wanted to
stay in this pet industry, so to say, decorated that.
So what we can do here, we can see the doctors, we can find
owners and owners have pets, for example, Eduardo Rodriguez,
Stool and Rosie, and for example, Julie's here and
has a broken leg.
And we can add it.
So that's more or less that.
That's very simple,
a very, very simple application, but it's more or less what I'm doing.
So I don't do that simple applications, but I'm doing business applications.
So we have UIs, data, stuff like that.
And what I did I reverse engineered
the pet clinic and that's a use case UML diagram by the way.
And this is quite helpful because on the diagram we have actors.
So you have two the visitor and the clinic user.
And these usually are also roles in the system.
And then we have like use cases they are grouped into parts or in modules
whatever.
So we have welcome page with the doctors then the owner management
the pet management.
And finally they visit or the management that I just did.
And when I do reverse engineering I just go on that level.
We also have an entity model.
So that's usually derived from the database model.
It depends if you have a SQL database or other database,
but usually you have information to cover that.
And here we have a diagram that just contains the types
that we can see how things are related in the system.
And then we have definition of of the entities.
I will talk about architecture in a minute,
because working like that or working with AI in my opinion,
has a huge impact on the architect styles or which architecture fits well.
And then we have created or reverse engineered the use cases.
Let's go and look at that one.
That's the the list of the doctors.
And here you can see that we have an actor.
We have preconditions scenarios.
And this one also contains an API that's irrelevant.
That was just reverse engineered.
And then we have post conditions.
And the post conditions are kind of acceptance criteria.
If you think about user stories that can be verified in tests to check
if the use case finally was successful.
And from that, because I have skills and everything I just call 'implement'.
So that means in those projects we don't prompt.
So we have skills for everything and we iterate on the skills.
So we try to improve them constantly.
We share the skills in the organization.
That's kind of a problem currently, because not
everybody in the organization is maybe using the same agent.
So we need some skill distribution.
I'm using Claude Code here.
I do things that I usually don't do.
So I don't run it here inside the ID.
That's just for for demo purposes.
And now it looks at that.
But I also have and.
What you heard in the last talk, if you were here in that room,
I have clothed me and this is more or less
has not much inside, but a very important part.
That is it.
Somewhere I can't find it, but somewhere there is a reference to some guidelines.
So we have guidelines for architecture, for example
how we structure the application, how the package looks like,
what tools we are using that they are in us about that.
But most of the things are in the skills.
And my process also comes with skills.
So if you go there, we don't have time to to look at that.
But if you go there and look at it, you see there are two levels of skills.
So we have skills primarily for specification
and their skills specific for one stack that I'm using.
But I stopped adding more skills for more stacks
because there are so many combinations out there that that's probably
a thing that the company has to do, and now it works on that.
And maybe I go back to this one because I was already talking about that.
In my opinion, the architecture has an impact on how well things work.
So first of all, in the past
15 years or so, we were doing microservices
and most of my customers did microservices in a very naive way.
So they have way too many microservices because they were focusing
on the micro in microservices.
And that's probably a problem.
So they have this distributed big bowl of mud.
So I'm working for an insurance company and they have around 500 microservices.
And that's kind of an impact because they also have kind of
500 micro front ends.
And they are kind of related. Right.
So we have an end to end relationship between front end and pack end.
And that's the worst case scenario.
Because if you have if you want to work with
AI on a certain part of your system, you have to have the context.
So you need the code that the AI should work on in a single place,
at least on your machine or wherever you work with that with AI.
And if you have five microservices, a lot of components somewhere,
and you have to mix and match that, that becomes very difficult.
Now there's a movement away from microservices
to monolithic or modular monolithic application.
And I would say stop here, don't do that because that's not the right way,
because maybe you have like a huge monolith that we have
currently pieces as thousands of database tables and a lot of modules.
And that's a problem, right?
Because the context is too big.
So how can we work on that?
And there's an architecture style that not so well known, but
it's approximately created when microservices were created.
It's called self-contained system.
And the self-contained system architecture just says we create verticals.
So we split our application into verticals, which has UIs, business
logic and database in one repo usually,
or in one project at least, where is one.
And if you have that, if you can split that and we do that
with the modernization, then the AI can exactly work on that.
And you can also add skills in depending on what technology you're using.
So for example, in the inventory system here we are using voting as I do
in my demo.
That's a web framework in Java.
But for the order management system for example we have react in the frontend.
So we can have different technology in different self-contained systems.
There's another thing that if you can stay on one stack.
So for example, if you stay with the Java stack or stay with the JavaScript
TypeScript stack or ecosystem, then probably creating order is simpler
because you need to create skills and all the stuff just for one technology.
Otherwise, if you do what my customers usually doing,
they have a single page framework like React or Angular,
and then usually spring boot or quarks in the backend,
they have to create this twice and also maintain that twice, right?
And once.
Another thing that's also quite interesting is the impact on the teams.
And that's the big change.
So for those a company that's relatively simple because that's not a huge team.
And they already work in maintenance mode.
So they don't really do scrum anymore right.
They don't have fixed sprints.
They work on depending on what features they have to implement.
But because we
use like the specs as an input, as we also kind of
did with the stories, by the way, in a, in a scrum
development way.
But we are very fast so we cannot wait to weeks.
So that's way too long.
So we need maybe two weeks to do the specification,
but we don't need to weeks to create the software.
And the other is reduce the team size.
We are per self-contained system, 1 to 2 developers,
preferable two because of knowledge exchange.
And maybe it's boring to work on a project alone,
but we reduce that from like 5 to 7 to 1 or 2.
And as I said, we do no more spins, we do continuous flow, and we use
the use cases in a Kanban way to track the progress.
That's all we do. Right?
Then something
that or we can go back that's probably done.
And what it created is just the implementation of that.
And now we have the list of doctors here.
So that's that's great.
Oh you're right I really don't like PowerPoint
because this changes everything.
So that was done.
It took 1.5 minute or so.
And now we see the doctors right.
So that's a simple use case.
But that's something that we have a lot in the system.
Something like that. Right.
And why did this work.
First of all because of this
guardrails that I was talking about.
So first of all, my recommendation never let AI create the project.
First of all, you just waste tokens if you do that.
But if you do that, you probably end up with an outdated application.
So if you have like spring, for example, in the trial field, there's Spring Initializr
that you can create an application,
you get the newest dependencies, you get in the way.
How the spring team currently thinks about creating applications.
Maybe you have a CLI for your tools.
Use that.
Don't use AI for that.
And then you have to define the rules.
So that means you don't put everything in Claude.md or in the AGENTS.md
because there's a study from the university in Zurich
and they say the bigger the system prompt,
more hallucinations you get probably.
So it's maybe even better to have none of those files than a big one.
And then you can add architecture.
So we usually to kind of architecture
or arc42.
That's kind of a format.
Or you can do architecture documentation.
Then we add skills. That's the important thing.
A lot of people were talking about that.
And we also have MCP source because skills shouldn't be that big.
And we have huge documentation, for example,
for in-house frameworks where we get MCP services vector
search that I can directly search in the documentation.
Right. That's how we do that.
And if you do a good job and iterate on that, you really get probably
a near deterministic solution.
So what I did before
I can delete everything to it again I will get more or less the same outcome.
Right. But very important.
The human should review depending, as I said on the risk.
What happens when your system doesn't work or have bugs?
Then you should probably go and add more reviews or depending on
if you do reviews by hand, or you use AI to review or however you work on that.
So we don't do pull requests.
By the way, at the moment we do trunk based development
and we do kind of an ongoing review process.
So we work on something and then we do peer reviews.
So we work if we are to developers, they work together and do the review together.
So they try to explain parts of the system that they created with the others.
So we don't pull requests anymore in those projects.
So to conclude, specs reduce not that enrichment but not specs are not enough.
So you need the harness.
You need all the context around that that this really works.
And something that I didn't talk about is in
my opinion, specs are very sustainable
or hopefully they will be sustainable in the future because currently
what I'm doing is reverse engineering of existing code into specs.
And if we have specs, we can probably generate
the same application in different technology with a different UI.
Maybe we don't have even a UI, we have chat or something directly
from the specs and the business people
can directly change the way the systems should behave without developer,
so they don't need developers talking about that or looking into that.
And this accelerates development.
The problem is at the moment.
It just accelerates development.
Right.
So the requirements phase and the spec phase takes some time.
For example I'm working for this government for the Parliament.
They are have a business case management software that we want to modernize.
And I'm the only one during the proof of concept doing something with code.
But we have two product only requirements engineers that work on the spec,
and they have much more work to do than I have, I trust automate everything.
So currently I'm working on on a pipeline that they can
just change the model files and everything will automatically generate it.
So the kind of the work moves or shifts left,
so everything shifts left to requirements engineering in my opinion,
because now that's obvious before we add like
if it did scrum, you had two weeks to work on the requirements somehow.
And then we are two weeks working on the implementation.
Now you have two weeks
and then five minutes and two weeks, something like that.
Right.
And the most important thing is you should know your architecture and domain.
And this will lead us to the discussion about the training developers.
But I think we stop here at this and that's it from my side.
Thank you very much.
Thank you so much, Simon.
We have a few minutes for questions if anyone would like to ask something.
Okay. We'll start here.
Thank you for nice hands on presentation.
I have a question about use cases.
Did I understand correctly that you initially generate diagram in plant.
And then from that diagram you generate detailed text requirements and markdown.
So usually you would
so on a greenfield project you would have like
requirements catalog or something or a product requirements document.
And from that I would first generate the use case diagram
that you have no review that we have.
And maybe this would even give you an idea how to split your application
into modules.
And then from that you can go ahead and generate that.
Because this music cases are kind of in the user story included, right.
It's just more detailed with all the steps.
And yeah, our requirements engineers and product
owners use AI a lot just to verify
the use cases to find maybe duplicates or things that are missing.
And they work a lot on on that with AI.
Yeah.
But we go use case by use case because a lot of people say spectrum
development is waterfall.
And that's simply not true.
It just is just requirements and then test and implementation.
But that's also the case with agile right.
You have to do that.
But we don't do pick up from design.
We just go use case by use case.
Maybe it's a follow up question.
But like say your user story is wrong and you need to update it.
What's the flow?
Do you regenerate the whole application?
Do you append a new requirement document?
I don't understand.
So if I have a use case for example, let's go here and I have.
What did I do before?
I think I did that one right.
And now I see okay there's but we have something here.
So it says that it displays the doctor with first name,
last name and the common separated list of specialties for example.
And now we could go ahead and say no that's not common.
Separate.
That's maybe.
Yet sign that I need to separate.
And what I would do now, I would go ahead and say
again, the same that I did before implement,
because at the moment we need the code or we read the code right.
And I don't want I could throw it away for sure,
but then my git history wouldn't look nice and it would be harder
to review the changes, right?
That would be an issue in my opinion or not in my opinion.
Opinions on some people is AI doesn't need the source code.
So I'm a travel developer.
That's bytecode that's executed.
AI could generate the bytecode.
There is no reason to generate the source code.
Maybe.
Or maybe we end up with the programing language that's more
AI friendly and less human readable, I don't know, but at the moment
we just work as you would if you would do that manually.
So we really changed use cases or the entity model.
And then we say just apply the changes.
I'm so sorry
there's so many more questions, but we are out of time.
You guys can hunt down Simon and ask him yourselves.
Our next session is going to be in ten minutes, but big round
of applause for Simon.